howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show com that's Jim rut show com
this is another of our special extra
episodes around coronavirus 19 and the
social political and other economic
implications of that of that shock to
our system
today's guest is Ben Gert sole who's
been on the show before and he's put out
some interesting tweets focusing on some
of the not-so-good things to expect on
the other side of the c19 outbreak I
think that's important for us to start
thinking about right now because whether
the Peaks gonna be in late April May
June it's not far off and unfortunately
what I'm seeing even from the best state
and national leaders is very
understandable focus on trying to
flatten the curve and dealing with the
shitstorm we have from the rising curve
but interestingly the managing the
backside of the curve is gonna be every
bit as important in fact maybe more
important to the long-term social and
economic health of our country so with
that let's jump in so Ben one of the
things you talked about is you know
we're already seeing it my daughter
who's 31 a lot of her friends working in
you know entry-level positions they're
all getting laid off right and many of
them are gonna be rehired the economy is
gonna restructure itself what are some
of your thoughts about that yeah I think
there's gonna be a lot of changes in the
economy and structure of society that
have been sort of poised and waiting to
happen but held back by sort of and
and then the disruption of of kovat 19
it triggers some changes that were sort
of provided in the structure of society
and you know it's it's hard to focus
ones attention on these medium term
economic and social issues when you were
buried am I gonna die next week or is my
grandma gonna die tomorrow right but on
the other hand we're gonna get through
the Cova 19 pandemic I mean it's it's
bad and people will die who I would much
rather didn't die but we're gonna get
through it we're gonna create vaccines
we're gonna find antiviral cocktails and
at the end of it
society is gonna be a little bit
different than before in ways that are
gonna be significant for many people and
in many ways not good not good for a lot
of people right so that you can see the
cinema in a bunch of different ways
directs I mean yeah one of them as as
you say Jim is a lot of service
employees are being laid off now and
there's clearly there's not be a patent
who's gonna get laid off and who listen
right so I mean if you're uh you know a
knowledge employee or if the term soul
is used I mean if you're if you're white
collar and you're working at your laptop
all day right all right at your at your
desk you know writing documents and
munching spreadsheets pretty much you
can still do that at home but your
meetings to zoom calls there's a bit of
loss of efficiency due to the you know
toddler flinging muck at your head while
you work at home but you know you're
still operational but if you're if
you're flipping burgers at McDonald's or
you know greeting people at the
department store or carrying out but
various jobs that are just face to face
human interaction I mean then there's
really no reason for your employer to
keep you employed during this sort of
flash depression we're seeing you to
Cove it and indeed your employer
probably can't afford to but then
once the : flash depression is over then
what happens in some cases you'll just
get hired back but in other cases your
employer will take a fresh look at the
situation of things like well maybe we
can do more online ongoingly even after
Koch has gone or maybe maybe you know
maybe now is the time to invest in some
automation technology to outsource this
or that so I think not all the service
employees laid off are gonna be rehired
and then you know at the same time smart
investors funds with piles of money
they're gonna be looking around now and
saying well like hey what can i what can
i buy up at a discount price during this
Depression because the you know the
owners to have the money to sustain for
six months without revenue or you know
what what comparators can I put out a
business because they they can't survive
in there on their cash stockpile but but
I can so you're gonna see major
consolidation in a variety of industry
so in short increasing wealth in the
hands of the wealthy and more unemployed
people becoming poorer and poorer at the
same time as more power is going to the
hands of big tech companies and big
government right because that the tech
lash is fading now everyone loves Amazon
and ever everyone loves Google and and
zoom and whatever tools give them their
lifeline in connection Facebook if their
lifeline in connection to that to the
outside world whether they're stuck at
home dealing with their suddenly much
more annoying family members right so I
mean tech lash is gone
no big banks and PE funds they're owning
more and more working-class people put
out of out of work and then you know
government will slowly put it better and
better surveillance mechanisms sucking
data from big tech so as to better
monitor the pandemic but then
whatever monitoring they put in place
for the pandemic is gonna keep going
right so we're looking toward more and
more of a sort of a fascist oligopoly
and oligarchy which is kind of what we
already have but we're acknowledging
further and further in in that direction
once this pandemic is gone at least no
none of us knows what the hell is gonna
happen but that seems like sort of the
the most likely course unless so they
even worse happens or unless some of us
crazy hackers and then freaks managed to
get some alternative systems wrong yep I
think that those are all spot-on
analyses you know I used a little bit I
use a framing for what comes after and I
say that we'll see a mix of homeostasis
and hysteresis homeostasis being a
biological mostly biological has a
chemical origin of systems that tend to
converge back to the way they were
hysteresis being a physics term for
systems that basically are influenced by
recent events and move off into new
directions and don't return and you know
an example I like to give is business
travel it's my firm prediction I've made
some adjustments in my portfolio to
represent this the business travel will
never return as you were saying things
that could happen but hadn't happened
because of inertia you know they were
sort of this game theoretic I have to
show you respect by flying to Hong Kong
for a one-hour meeting waste of time and
money at pretty gist Porsche III I think
you're wrong on that one but we can play
some better of it because I for
psychological reasons you're wrong I
think of other people are gonna get sick
and right now with their husband and
kids or wife and kids and that they will
be very eager to very easy to resume
business trouble just for personal
reasons I'll bet you let's do it let's
phrase a bet now I'll bet see any
reasonable stake because I do believe
people do need to get back to work for
most people working for home is not
sustainable
but fly halfway across the world for a
one-hour business meeting absurd when
you could spent when you could do three
one
our zooms and get much more work done
whoa I think as often it will probably
be a bit of each right yes I say it's a
mix of hysteresis and homeostasis
regarding business travel in particular
which which may not be the best thing
for us to dig into in great depth but I
mean I think you're right that like if V
sees get used to closing investment
deals buy a conference call then they're
gonna know like yeah I can close
investment deals via a conference call
so we don't always need to wait in order
to for someone to meet face to face in
order to do it right so that I think
that could be a genuine acceleration and
efficiency improvement because I mean
now now you have beasties and so I can
valley vine to close a deal with some
hot startup in uh no New York or Atlanta
or somewhere but they still wait to
close until people can fly around the
meet face to face right so if they get
in their head that they don't need to do
that then you know the competition will
happen in a bunch of video calls and
things will happen even even faster so I
think yeah there definitely will be
cases like that on the other hand as
someone who speaks at a bunch of events
I can see that the sort of connections
you make at conferences and events isn't
happening now I mean what the kind of
networking one can do now is great for
those of us who are old and walnut or
can already know a lot of people but in
the current scheme of things in this
comment period there's no way for new
people just entering an industry or an
area of research to to build to build
their social network like online online
conferences really really don't cut it
second life doesn't doesn't cut it so
you know if the oh there's up sniffing
in the summer there's a shitstorm of
events that are postponed till September
and in October so I mean one test will
be you know how much of these events
that were supposed to be in spring
postponed till September and October
like how much are they flooded with
people and I think I think as soon in
Kobe clears up in the storm of
astoundingly with people I think that's
a good distinction between conferences
and just routine business travel which
there's so goddamn much I think so it
won't be binary but let's move on to the
bigger questions the point the point
that you make I think is the is the
overriding one is that unfortunately and
without some interventions or revolt of
the masses this is a step function event
of the big getting bigger and the rich
getting richer you know for instance my
wife and I talked about oh yeah we
should sign up for the Kroger you know
order online pick it up
grocery thing but we never did and we
continued to you know hit various small
specialty stores the local hippie co-op
etc well guess what in the in the age of
the plague we quickly mastered you know
all three of the major grocery chain
order in advance and you know have it
delivered into the back of your car
services and I can tell you we're gonna
continue to use those things and the
percentage of our wallet share that goes
to the hippie co-op and to the little
funky small grocery store is gonna go
down and we'll try to resist that
because well yeah I mean so here now I
mean I'm on Vashon Island near near
Seattle right now and you know an awful
lot of live music clubs in Seattle where
I know the musicians who play their
proprietors I mean they're they're
shutting down though because there's no
gigs and no audiences but most of these
guys aren't gonna start new live music
clubs it was pretty marginal in the
first place right so you could see a
whole new crop of little loud music
venues pop up but I'm um I'm kind of
dabbing it actually actually actually so
that I think yeah there's a lot of
things that we're waiting to happen and
cut back by inertia and they're given a
nudge here there's an example where
things may reconfigure I happen to know
some people in the you know kind of
grassroots music business and they've
been telling me for years that the
business has been moving from the club's
to what we're called home concerts where
a musician and a home owner who's a fan
will get
together and offer a concert charge 10
bucks or 20 bucks and you know three
quarters of it or 90% of it will go to
the musician and 10% will go to the
homeowner to cover the cost of chips and
water and the musician will make a lot
more money than they were making in the
clubs and the homeowner had this very
cool experience of one of their favorite
niche musicians actually doing a concert
in their home so maybe we'll see a
reconfiguration more strongly to those
home concerts I mean there's a lot of
ways things could happen and you know
you can play outdoors in a public park
whether what where the climate is warm
you can you can plan it in a restaurant
right but I guess the common trend will
be this shift will be took things that
are lower costs to operate and involve
less you know working-class human labor
and that's gonna be I would say a common
denominator among these things and then
shifting to home concerts is sort of
then again to shift toward the gig
economy right okay the guy who's Houston
is is temporarily like playing the role
that would be would be plagued by the by
the club owner but probably making less
money than the club owner does the other
game has no cost right has no variable
cost it has that yeah so it actually
ends up being more profitable but just
it reconfigures how assets are used and
this shock will cause a lot of that and
you know I'm suggesting to people who
really want to think about the back side
of the curve which is coming very
rapidly I have to keep reminding people
of that this peak will be you know late
April May June maybe and the backs
managing the back side of the curb is
gonna be a much bigger and more
important task for society than trying
to flatten the curve is because we're
you know we're very much Adelina
go ahead so the case the case of music
concerts is one where it may all be fun
anyway like we've already gotten rid of
Tower Records and so on you can
distribute your music through the
internet and you can play locally and
somebody's backyard now the case of like
retail supply chains and of you know
retail being reduced to only like
Walmart Don and and Target or something
I mean this this comes down to a
corporate hegemony thing where than if
you're if you're selling a product but
none of these outlets want to sell
there's no way to get it to anyone right
and so I mean I mean in a lot of domains
you've seen things narrow focus to just
a few outlets so it almost becomes like
a variant of that the dreaded old
communist system where you just have to
buy everything online from the
government's reach out or something and
these of course these big tech companies
that are monopolizing things large
retailers they are in fact closely tied
with the government for better or worse
like I'm an Amazon and Microsoft putting
huge news server farms right right and
and bodies of staff right next to the
Pentagon so I mean we're we're moving
through the combination of social
factors like this Kovach pandemic and
then just economies of scale in
technology I mean we're we're moving
toward an oligopoly that is hard to
break without busting out of the
traditional ways of doing things right
and that's something that's been
frustrating to me as something who's
been you know participating in the
blockchain and crypto ecosystem through
singularly net which is the AI based
blocking base a marketplace I've been
working on for the last couple years I
mean crypto and blockchain were sort of
supposed to be forming alternatives to
all these centralized hegemonic methods
right like when when there was a global
financial crisis it's supposed to be
Bitcoin that comes out as as the new
gold or the new global reserve currency
or something in them instead of Amazon
we're supposed to have some
decentralized token based system for you
know a small side
some things to customers with a smart
decentralized reputation system and then
you know as it is happening when the
worlds in this situation where this sort
of thing would really really be useful
it's not ready for primetime right I
mean the US dollar is supreme again the
flight to quality look like always in
the financial crunch and then you know
decentralized market places are very
either very specialized or just too
crude to do anything and if you
ultimately if you need to order a bunch
of stuff you got a good Amazon present
the question is like bye-bye the next
big crisis being a pandemic or like a
global rash of of cyber attacks bringing
down the power grid or whatever they
whatever the big next crisis is and
there probably will be one right then
then will alternative mechanisms be
there yet to even be part of this story
is now in the current crisis they're not
really part of this story unfortunately
that is true you know again you know
I've been working on this thing with
some friends called game B which is a
still fairly sketchy vague I should say
new social operating system operating
with much more localism much more
ability to sever the networks without
bad things happening etc but we're you
know still years away from being ready
to be an alternative social operating
system so I'm taking this as a wake-up
call rather than saying we have you know
30 or 40 years to figure it out I'm at
least taking it as a personal mission to
say we got to figure this thing out
before the next one I think your you
know your point is well-taken
none of the also that's the question
right how many how many people will take
this as a wake-up call in various ways
and that's not entirely clear right I
mean like you know of course what
happened to dusty as ski the Russian
Roger like he was putting from the
firing squad goes home to his head then
you know they fired it it turns out to
be blanks and after coming back close to
death you know after that he's like wow
every minute
is amazing what like life is wonderful I
will cherish each moment and that that
lasted like six months or something for
them then you went back to grumbling
about how knowing life is like I mean
that that's the homeostasis right so
that the question is how many people who
are getting a wake-up call now will get
it go to sleep cause six months late and
when things seem to be back to normal
that's I mean that's what happens after
every financial bubble and financial
crash right after another six months or
year people start thinking again that
another crash can never happen again
yeah and here's my view on this I've
been thinking about this hard which is I
do not believe this is the revolutionary
time for the reasons you articulated
that the infrastructure just isn't there
yet however a lot of people are being
woken up I'm talking to a bunch of them
and so I believe this epoch post the
back side of the curve in the next six
months that's a good time this is the
time to build the cadre we may be able
to build the cadre by a factor of ten or
twenty people whose ears have been open
by this big basically force applied to
them they've been forced to think about
life and death for the first time ever
in their life for a lot of men that's
Americans and so basically many more
ears will be open so I personally and
people I know are gonna be putting forth
a blitz to try to recruit grow our cadre
which we might call our game be spaced
10,000 people let's see if we can grow
into a quarter million by the end of the
year and then from that basis there'll
be enough skill sets and they'll be
enough leaders that perhaps we can build
a faster route to spin up so that when
the next crisis comes and it is coming
whether it's one climate-related a food
pandemic with you might be right
I mean I think people have been woken up
to some extent to the fact that things
aren't quite as stable predictable and
necessary as they had thought right like
to to some of us that's always been been
obvious that
the status quo is kind of fragile and
then you could have a massive disruption
at any time but most people's don't
think that way and their minds are blown
that what the I can't go he
defeated a restaurant now what the hell
is going on but airfare from Seattle to
Boston is ten dollars each way hop in
the space to people who really weren't
thinking that things could be so
radically disrupted I mean not now
they've got that in their head and that
but that does give an opening and that
this is part of our thinking with this
kovat 19 decentralized a hackathon the
covetous thumb organize the singularity
net together with that with notion
protocol and decentralized AI lines
right like they the proximal goal which
is a real one this like let's get
Packers are laying on blockchain who are
finding themselves perhaps with an
unusual amount of free time now you know
that let's get the marking creating code
that can be useful to help with the Cova
19 situation I mean maybe some some code
that allows decentralized mechanisms to
serve some useful functions now on the
other hand you know what we're also
looking this as an opportunity to
aggregate together a whole bunch of
hackers with an enthusiasm that hasn't
been there before using AI to combat
like global social issues right and some
it may be in the optimal case there's
something useful for code 19 and then we
keep going the group afterwards and you
have you know a more integrated network
of decentralized AI hackers you know
building the infrastructure that will
let us deal better with the next crisis
when it comes because yeah of course the
next crisis is going to come like look
at the whole world infrastructure I mean
that the major nations of the world are
run by are run by what kinds of people
right I mean how how stable is is as the
banking system I mean it's a every major
system that regulates life on the planet
has some extreme
corruption or degeneration is it right
and that's it it's amazing that things
even operate as well as they do on an
everyday basis but there certainly
there's certainly not robust enough to
keep going to the technological
singularity without a series of further
crises probably some much worse than the
Komen nineteen crisis exactly I've been
calling this the mini apocalypse right
unlikely that the basic infrastructure
goes down electricity and water things
like that not that I would not make that
next same guarantee about the next one
you have to go and so do I so let's
spend the next five minutes on a little
bit of a counter trend to what we've
been talking about one of my takeaways
when I think about our game be movement
in particular is I'll confess it has
sort of a hippie dippie flavor
decentralized building proto bees that
communicate with each other through you
know protocols that we all agree upon in
advance an emergent justice system etc
all sounds like a right great way to
live but unfortunately doesn't
necessarily a great way to be able to
respond in real-time decisively against
the crisis so I think a challenge to all
of us who are thinking about
decentralized social operating systems
we need need now to use this event and I
would also postulate a more severe
version and we essentially say that our
decentralized social operating system
needs to be able to have the near
real-time command and control
capabilities like this I think the
current US response to come in nineteen
industries very well the weakness of
centralized control systems right
because I mean you you have a food in
chief in charge of the US who is the
centerpiece of a centralized control
system and because that one component is
cognitively and emotionally faulty I
mean then the response of the whole US
system was slower than it should have
been and China's response demonstrated
the same thing right I mean at the top
they had a system for suppressing
freedom of press and freedom of
information and the top level of the
central
control system caused the initial
response to be too slow even though the
response of China a little afterwards
became became highly efficient in many
ways so yeah I think it's clear that a
well-crafted decentralized response
system can be much much better than the
centralized systems we have we have now
for the exact reason that the
centralized system is is too too
susceptible to failing to the witnesses
at the center which is exactly exactly
what we've we've seen but you do I mean
you need a effective well-designed
decentralized system not as well
designed but fully implemented and and
tested and and unfortunately we don't
have that yet not because it's not
possible
technologically or conceptually just as
insanely much more resources have gone
into creating and maintaining the
centralized systems because the
resources are controlled by the people
in power of the central us exactly how
do we get the D central I agree with you
absolutely agree with you that this is a
demonstration of the failure of game a
and its over reliance on a single faulty
part and of course it's not just in the
u.s. most of the West has also failed
you know Italy and Spain looks like
England and France are also gonna suffer
hard Sweden's not doing well so it's not
just our own faulty part there's uh you
know you're right and in the Trump is
just an especially colorful example but
it's a it's a systemic you know I do
agree that's that the centralized
systems ought to do better but we have
to start thinking about them in terms of
dealing with problems of this magnitude
not just in a hippie-dippie way how we
live our life in a better way and I
think that's one of my big takeaways in
one of my communications obligations
going forward is to make sure that what
we're thinking about these protocols and
I know you guys have been doing that was
your singularity that you know how do we
deal with the biggest problems you know
say lian's and may the earth or you know
a true yeah you're right I mean you
wanna
want to appear to all the reptile
emotions so we will appeal to lust but
also to to fear right so I mean that I
think and people sort of they they need
to understand all the dimensions of this
situation or that respond appropriately
and understanding not only how wonderful
an anarchist utopia we can create with
decentralized tools and methods but also
how scary the world can be if we don't
have those decentralized methods to
protect us from a bunch of I mean
all all these aspects are important to
appealing to human motivational systems
right which is which is what is what
needs to be done if we're gonna leverage
human energy because it's toward
building an alternative to decentralized
systems and control the world now
because it you know it's very possible
to create decentralized networks that
work much much more efficiently than the
centralized systems controlling the
world now but it is hard right I mean
it's not it's it's really even something
is as simple as you know a decentralized
efficient payment system which the
crypto world is working on for a long
time I mean it's true that's possible
but there's just a lot of algorithm and
implementation work to be done there and
and to make a whole decentralized
operating system for the world there's a
whole lot of pieces like that that I'll
have to all have to work together we
absolutely have the technology and the
brainpower on the planet to do it but
with people need to be energized and
motivated in that Anette directions so
yeah if this pandemic serves to wake up
enough people with relevant skills and
resources to the the need for building
it and alternative decentralized
infrastructure I mean then then the
pandemic in hindsight will appear like
an extremely positive thing for the
evolution of humanity let's end it right
there we both got to go Thank You Ben
for a very interesting perspective as
always
yeah yeah thanks thanks for the good
questions and yeah looking forward to
next time very good talk to you soon bye
bye
woman production services and audio
editing by Jared Jane's consulting music
by Tom Muller at modern space music.com
[Music]